原视频名：Did An Engine Failure Kill A SpaceX Booster on Its 6th Flight
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/QXTIt5WIKoE
原视频发布日期：20210216
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Last night SpaceX added another 60 satellites to their Starlink constellation
昨晚 SpaceX又给他们的Starlink星座增加了60颗卫星
using a booster which had flown on five previous missions.
使用了已执行过五次任务的助推器
It started flying back in December 2019 carrying Dragon CRS-19 to the space station.
早在2019年12月 这枚一级火箭就开始飞行 那时搭载了CRS-19任务的龙飞船 飞往国际空间站
And yeah it carried a NROL-108, SAOCOM-1B.
是的 它还搭载了NROL-108 SAOCOM-1B
The booster serial number was 1059.
助推器的序列号是1059
All in all this was a standard mission and it was a successful mission.
总而言之这是一次标准任务 也是一次成功的任务
It did put all 60 Starlink satellites into orbit
它确实把所有60颗星链卫星送入了轨道
and now thanks to better communications we get some really good footage of this happening.
而现在多亏了更好的通信 我们看到了这很好的(星箭分离的)画面
Previously we would lose signal when these bars came off the side
以前当这些杆子从旁边脱落的时候 会失去信号
but now we get to see the whole deployment.
但现在我们可以看到整个部署过程
But the bad news is that SpaceX did not recover the booster
但坏消息是 SpaceX并没有回收助推器
and that in itself is now becoming a news story
而这本身就已经成为了一个新闻
and everybody's asking me to talk about it.
每个人都要我谈论它
So yeah what we saw was in the background of the landing ship
那么 是的 这部分视频是在着陆船的背景中
some orange glow in the sky and that was it.
天空中出现了一些橙色的光芒 就这些
The seagulls barely even bothered.
海鸥几乎不理会
And that's a bit of a shame
这是一个有点可惜的事情
because well seagulls are the flying rats of the sea
因为海鸥是海上的飞行老鼠啊
and I would have loved to seen a rocket land in the middle of them and show it who's boss.
我很想看到一枚火箭降落在它们中间 让它知道谁说了算
So I shall cope with this disappointment by instead analyzing this in every way I know
那么为了应对这种失望的情绪 我将用我所知道的各种方式来分析这个问题
because that's sort of my coping mechanism.
因为这算是我的某种应对机制
As luck would have it there was another Starlink launch a couple of weeks ago on February 3rd
运气好的是 几周前的2月3日 就有一场星链的发射
and it had practically the same flight profile
而它的飞行轨迹几乎是一样的
so looking at the performance all the way up through the initial boost and to the ignition of the second stage
因此 从最初的发射到二级的点火 这些表现看下来
everything looked practically the same right.
几乎都是一样的
There was small deviations in the numbers
数字有小的偏差
but it looks like the booster performed perfectly
但看起来助推器表现完美
and of course everything got into orbit so that's not unsurprising.
但当然 一切(载荷)都进入了轨道 所以这并不奇怪
So six minutes 20 seconds into the flight we're getting ready for the entry burn
所以在飞行6分20秒后 再入点火准备好将要进行
that is where the booster lights up three of its engines to slow itself down
此时 助推器要点燃三台发动机来减速
and make sure it doesn't hit the atmosphere too hard.
并确保它不会过度撞击大气层
This is done on all the booster recoveries.
所有的助推器回收时都会这样做
You're looking on the left here the one on the right is just the vehicle in orbit.
左边的画面就是助推器 右边那个是在轨道上的二级火箭
Now after it slows down enough it shuts down those engines.
那么当它完成了足够的减速后 它就会关闭那些发动机
And that glow is supposed to go away except that it doesn't go away.
而发动机的光芒本该消失 但并没有消失
We end up with this bright flash which looks decidedly on nominal.
我们最终看到的是这个明亮的闪光 很明显 看起来是正常的
It's normal to see flashes of light at this point as it hits the atmosphere going several times the speed of sound
这时看到闪光是正常的 因为一级火箭正以数倍音速的速度撞击大气层
but the sustained burn is wrong and then we lose the telemetry.
但持续的点火是有问题的 接着我们失去了遥测信号
If you look in the bottom left corner that is the stage one telemetry and that is now frozen.
你可以看下左下角 那是一级火箭的遥测数据 而现在已经停住了
Bottom right we have the stage two telemetry that keeps going.
右下角是二级火箭那还在继续变化的遥测数据
And we don't get any further updates on the vehicle.
在一级火箭上 我们没有得到任何进一步的更新
We don't get any call outs for the vehicle going transonic or the landing burns starting.
我们没听到这些呼号 比如一级火箭亚音速 以及着陆点火开始
All we get is that orange glow on the left side and that's it.
我们只得到了左侧这橙色的光芒 就这些
So yeah let's compare it with the launch from a couple of weeks ago.
那么 是的 让我们把它与几周前的发射进行比较
So on the left is last night's flight. On the right is the older flight.
那么左边是昨晚的飞行 右边是更旧的飞行
I've synchronized these in terms of altitude not in terms of the clock.
我已经按照高度而不是时间 把视频进行了同步
The clock is slightly different because it took a few more seconds in one case
时间略有不同 因为其中一次飞行多花了几秒时间
but you'll see that they pretty much light their engines at the same time.
但你会发现 他们几乎是同时进行发动机点火的
Initially they just light the center engine and then a second or so later they light two more engines
一开始他们只点燃了中间的发动机 一秒钟左右后他们又点燃了另外两台发动机
and they use three engines for the burn.
之后他们使用了三台发动机进行点火
So we're going to use those telemetry numbers in the bottom left of the screen to analyze this.
那么我们要用屏幕左下角的遥测数字来分析这件事
We're going to use them to make graphs because while all that fire and flames looks pretty hot and sexy
我们要用它们来做图 因为尽管所有的火焰看起来都很好
they don't tell you the story.
但你不能从中搞清楚这件事
So here you are a graph of acceleration versus time.
那么这是加速度与时间的关系图
Those are one second ticks along the bottom.
底部的刻度为一秒
The blue line is last night's booster.
蓝线是昨晚的助推器
The red line is the known good booster.
红线是已知的运行良好的助推器
And you can see, it ticks along and it rises up quickly.
你可以看到 随着时间的增加 加速度迅速上升
There's a little bump there.
那里有个小小的突起(而不是平缓地上升)
That's the lag between lighting the first engine and lighting the other two engines.
那是因为另外两台发动机的点火略微滞后于第一台发动机
They both reach peak of about 40 meters per second
它们都达到了40m/s²的峰值
but then the blue line drops off down to just above 30 meters per second per second acceleration.
但蓝线下降到30m/s²多的加速度
So that's about a 25 percent loss of thrust
那么推力损失了大约25%
and 25 percent is the number I would have expected
而25%是我预期的数字
because if you have three engines and one of them fails you expect a 33 percent change.
因为如果你有三台发动机 其中一台出现故障 就会有33%的变化
Maybe the center engine is under throttled for this burn.
也许中间的发动机在这次燃烧中节流过度
I don't know. I don't think so.
我不知道 我不这么认为
But it looks to me as if we definitely had a major engine failure
但在我看来 发动机肯定发生了重大故障
but it continued to operate and provide thrust at a significantly lower level
但它继续以低得多的推力水平运行并提供推力
for about five or six seconds before they all shut down.
差不多是在所有发动机关闭前的5到6秒时间
And that means that by the time the entry burn ends,
而这也就意味着 在再入点火结束的时候
there's a difference of about 150 kilometers per hour
两者的速度相差41.7m/s左右
which isn't a huge amount I'm gonna say given that they're moving at about 5800 kilometers per hour
我想说的是 这不是一个巨大的数字 考虑到火箭正以1600m/s的速度移动
but last night's flight is headed into the atmosphere steeper and faster
但昨晚的飞行正以更快更陡的速度进入大气层
and you can see it getting ahead here.
而在这时你可以看到它更快
And actually if you look at the the far right of that graph,
而实际上 如果你看这张图的右边
you'll notice that the blue line goes up faster
你会发现蓝线上升得更快了
because it's going deeper into the atmosphere and experiencing more drag
因为它更深入大气层 经历更多的阻力
so that is getting slowed down by the atmosphere more compared to the the old one
所以 与以前的发射相比 这会被大气层拖慢更多的速度
which is having a much more chill time.
而在以前的发射中 这一段时间更加平静
And so the next event is that we lose the telemetry. It becomes frozen.
那么下一个事件是我们失去了遥测信号 数字停住了
I'm just going to fast forward through this section
这部分我快进掉
because we want to get to where we see the cameras on the ships and we see the landing burns.
因为我们想看着陆船上的摄像头拍下的着陆点火的镜头
So the vehicle comes down. It's decelerating under drag.
那么一级火箭下降了 它在阻力下减速
It goes subsonic and then at this point it's aiming towards the ship.
它进入了亚音速状态 而在此刻 它的目标是船
Now on the left as soon as we switch over we see this pulsing orangish glow
那么一切到左边的画面 我们就看到这个脉冲式的橙黄色光芒
whereas we see nothing on the right until a few seconds later
而我们在右边什么也没看到 直到几秒钟后
and that's the actual light.
而这才是实际的光照
Now notice the difference in the color here.
那么注意这里的颜色差异
The one on the right has known good engine so it has a bright efficient flame.
右边的那个一级火箭有着已知的好发动机 那么它的火焰也是明亮高效的
The one on the left obviously had some sort of malfunction.
左边的那个显然有某种故障
But also what to realize is that these two things finished their entry burn at the same time
但也要意识到 这两枚一级火箭都同时完成了着陆点火
and yet we saw fire on the left way before we saw the landing burns start on the right.
但我们注意到左边的点火早在右边开始着陆前就已经在进行了
And if we look at this screenshot from the moment that we lost the telemetry
而如果我们看下这个屏幕截图 在我们失去遥测信号的那一刻起
you'll notice that the one on the right the good one has actually is actually going faster now
你就会注意到右边的那枚好的一级火箭实际上跑得更快了
because it was higher up and had less drag so it is actually catching up.
因为它的位置较高 阻力较小 所以实际上是在追赶左边的一级火箭
Therefore while the one with the damaged engine should have did initially get ahead
因此 虽然发动机受损的那枚一级火箭最初应该是领先的(在高度上)
the other one should have been catching up and they shouldn't be so far apart with the ignition.
另一枚应该会追上它 而两者的(着陆)点火不应该相距过大
The other thing is that there are low clouds over the Atlantic during both of these landings.
另一件事则是 在这两次降落的时候 大西洋上空都有较低的云层
You can actually see the clouds get illuminated
实际上你可以看到云层被照亮了
and then when the vehicle comes below the clouds, they get illuminated from below and it's very obvious.
然后当火箭来到云层下方的时候 云层就会被下方的火箭照亮 非常明显
So I'm thinking the one on the left may not actually have been an ignition.
那么我想左边那个可能不是一次点火
It may have simply been burning on its way down.
它可能只是在下降的途中就着火了
I can't know this for sure I don't have any special insider information but it sort of makes sense.
我不能确定这一点 我没有任何特殊的内幕消息 但这有点道理
If we assume that during the entry burn, one of the engines goes out quite likely the center engine,
如果我们假设在再入点火过程中 其中一台发动机坏了 很可能是中间的那台发动机
it renders the vehicle in a state where it will ultimately break during the re-entry
它使火箭处在这种状态下 也就是最终会在再入的过程中损坏
because of damage to the heat shield on the bottom.
因为底部的隔热板会损坏
The underperforming engine on its own probably isn't enough to cause the heat shield to fail.
单纯的发动机性能不佳可能还不足以导致隔热板失效
After all it's 150 kilometers per hour out of 6000.
毕竟这只是1667m/s中的41.7m/s (相当于只有2.5%的差异)
Since we only saw a 25 throttle drop that seems to say that we still had some performance from the engine
既然我们只看到了推力下降了25% 那似乎说明发动机还是有一定的性能的
which would say to me that the turbo pumps the fuel pump and the oxidizer pump are still working
这对我来说 涡轮泵 或者说燃料泵和氧化剂泵仍在工作
but something downstream from that is broken
而是更下游的东西坏了
and it's not really generating that much thrust.
而这导致它并没有真正产生那么大的推力
It's throwing a bunch of propellant out the back and that's what we're seeing burning here.
它把一堆推进剂从后面扔了出来 这就是我们看到在燃烧的东西
Whatever's happened I think is responsible for the telemetry being lost.
不管发生了什么 我想这都是导致遥测信号丢失的原因
I don't think that SpaceX turned off the telemetry because if you look at the speed right as it goes out.
我不认为时SpaceX关闭了遥测信号 因为如果你注意信号刚消失时的速度
It's the change slows down so it's like they're losing data and then the data stops
它的变化变慢了 那么就像他们失去了数据 然后数据停止了
And so at that point I don't think that SpaceX mission control have access to the vehicle
所以 在这一点上 我不认为SpaceX的任务控制能获取到一级火箭的数据
which is why we're not hearing any of the call-outs.
这就是为什么我们没有听到任何的呼号
Likely at this point they suspect that there's been some damage.
很可能在此时 他们已经在怀疑一些损伤的发生了
And it's not going to be able to land the booster.
而且助推器也将无法着陆
Meanwhile just continue on a ballistic trajectory rather than using its aerodynamics
同时只是继续沿着弹道轨迹前进 而不会使用空气动力(调整弹道)
and yet it just may be burning as it heads down below the clouds and that's what we see.
然而 它可能一直燃烧到云层下面 也就是我们看到的
Another bit of evidence to suggest that it might be burning and spinning
而另一个证据表明 它可能在燃烧并旋转
is just the fact that you see that thing pulsing as it comes down
这能说明在它下降的时候闪烁
which could be evidence for the vehicle rotating and burning.
这可能是火箭旋转并燃烧的证据
I highly doubt that is all correct.
我非常怀疑这一切是否完全正确
That's just one set of things that fits the parameters.
这只是符合参数的一组假设
It might not be the center engine.
出问题的发动机可能不是中心发动机
It could be one of the other engines
也可能是其他发动机之一
and then you still get fuel burning up inside the bottom of the rocket that causes something to fail.
然后还是会在火箭底部燃烧起燃料 导致一些东西失效
It could be an aerodynamic failure.
这可能是一个空气动力学方面的故障
It could actually be trying to light the engine
它实际上可能是在试图点燃发动机
and just burning in an awful nominal way and piling into the ocean.
而导致了糟糕而错误的点火 并坠入大海
It's hardly a big setback for SpaceX.
对SpaceX来说 这几乎不算什么重大挫折
This booster has flown six times successfully that is five more times than most rockets.
这台助推器已经成功飞行了六次 比大多数火箭多了五次(指一次性火箭)
SpaceX are probably already compiling a report for NASA
SpaceX可能已经在为NASA编写一份报告了
who will of course be interested since they put people on these rockets
而NASA当然会对此感兴趣 因为他们要把人放在这些火箭上
and any failure even if it's a failure after it's done its primary mission.
而任何故障 即使是在它完成主要任务后的故障
They are going to be interested to make sure it won't affect an actual ascent.
他们都会很感兴趣 以确保它不会影响实际的上升段飞行
SpaceX is out here pushing the reusability further than they have in the past.
SpaceX在这里将比过去 更进一步推动可重复使用性
And they're aiming to get 10 launches out of these rockets.
而他们的目标是用这些火箭进行10次发射
And well they're working upwards towards that
同时他们正朝着这个目标努力着
but even if they can only get half that they're still going to be way better than other rocket companies.
但即使他们只能重复使用5次 也会比其他火箭公司好很多
We also got an Elon tweet confirming that the active fairing half was recovered
我们还得到了马一龙的推特确认 主动整流罩的一半被回收了
and I think what they mean by active is that's the one with the pneumatic latch release mechanism
我想他们说的主动是指有气动锁扣释放装置的那半边
so if you look on the fairing that the camera is mounted on
那么 如果你看装有摄像头的那半边整流罩
there's a line of pressure lines around the outside
外围有一排加压管路
and that's what's used to release all the latches that hold the two fairings half.
而这些管路就会被用来释放所有固定两半整流罩的锁扣
And if you look at the other half as I reset the video,
而如果你看另一半整流罩 当然我重播了视频
you'll see it doesn't have this line along the fairing interface.
你会看到它没有沿着整流罩接口边缘的这条管路
So I think that's what they're talking about there.
那么我想这就是他们所说的
And I had to mention this
而我得提下这件事
because it gave me another reason to play this awesome piece of footage once more.
因为它给了我另一个理由 让我再播放一次这令人赞叹的视频
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全